Now, this one is a very important kind of communication that many a times freelancers or
والآن، فأنت في مرحلة مهمة جدًا من التواصل يفشل فيها الكثير من
people working at full-time jobs fail to do leading to bigger problems later.
موظفي العمل الحر أو موظفي الدوام الكامل، ويؤدي الفشل إلى مشاكل كبيرة لاحقًا.
Life doesn't go always as expected and things keep changing.
فالحياة لا تسير دائمًا كما نريد وكل شيء يتغير بسرعة.
Digital freelancing is no different.
والعالم الإلكتروني الرقمي يتغير أيضًا بسرعة.
But many a times you would foresee something as a blocker
ولكن في كثير من الأحيان قد تتوقع عقبات
to your plans for the project even before it comes.
لخطط مشاريعك حتى قبل ظهورها.
For example, based on the current base of the project,
فعلى سبيل المثال: استنادًا إلى حالة المشروع القائم،
you could assess if you're not on track to meet the deadline.
يمكن أن تتوقع أنك لن تستطع الوفاء بموعد التسليم النهائي.
Or maybe there's a change on your person end
أو قد يحدث لك أمر ما
which could affect the deadline agreed for the client.
يؤثر على إمكانية التزامك بموعد التسليم النهائي للعميل.
Sometimes there could be dependencies on other people
وفي بعض الأحيان قد تكون هناك مهام تتوقف على أشخاص آخرين
working for the client that you foresee not being met on time.
من طرف العميل نفسه، ولا يتم الوفاء بها في الوقت المحدد.
All of these is okay,
لا بأس من كل ذلك،
and part of any project.
فهذه أمور لا تتجزأ من أي مشروع.
Clients do understand delays that are within reason.
العملاء يتفهمون تأخير التسليم مادام في حدود المنطق.
What is not okay is not keeping the client in
يصبح الأمر سيئًا عندما لا تُخبر العميل
the loop of any foreseeable delays or blockers in the project.
بالتأخيرات المتوقعة أو العقبات الموجودة في المشروع.
This could lead to client frustration and give rise to blame game later.
مما يؤدي إلى إحباط العميل فيلوم عليك لاحقًا.
Now, in many cases,
والآن في كثير من الحالات،
we as freelancers,
فنحن كموظفين في مجال العمل الحر
may think that even though the time is limited,
نعتقد أنه برغم محدودية الوقت
we might just be able to meet the deadline.
نستطيع الالتزام بالموعد النهائي.
That's a good thing but giving your client a heads
هذا أمر جيد، ولكن يجب تنبيه العميل
up will make them prepared in case you're not able to do that.
ليكون مستعدًا في حال لم تستطع الوفاء بموعد التسليم.
In fact, they might be able to prioritize some of the stuff or
في الواقع قد تستطيع ترتيب أولويات بعض الأشياء أو
reduce the scope of the deliverable for that deadline if they are in the norm.
تقليص نطاق التسليم للوفاء بالموعد النهائي، إن كان ذلك في حدود المقبول.
However, if you do meet the deadline,
وبالرغم من ذلك فإن استطعت الالتزام بالموعد النهائي للتسليم،
it would be wonder for them and they'll be glad and
سيكون ذلك محل إعجاب
appreciate the extra effort you put in to meet the deadline.
وتقدير من طرف العميل، حيث أنك قمت بمجهود إضافي للوفاء بموعد التسليم.
At the end I would say,
وفي النهاية أود أن أقول
avoid understanding the importance of a heads up to the client.
أن تنبيه العميل وإعلامه بأي عقبات، أمر هام جدًا.
After all, this will demonstrate your interest in maximizing value for the client,
بعد كل شيء، سيظهر هذا اهتمامك بتعظيم القيمة للعميل،
and the fact that you respect their timeline and their commitments.
ويوضح له احترامك لجدوله الزمني والتزاماته.
Now, when a client starts a freelancing project,
عندما يبدأ العميل مشروع حر،
they have a big picture in mind,
يكون لديه صورة كبيرة في ذهنه،
the final goal that they want to achieve through the project.
تتعلق بالهدف النهائي الذي يريد الوصول إليه من خلال المشروع.
When you wear client's heart and try to maximize their value,
عندما تضع نفسك في مكان العميل وتضع مصلحته أولًا،
you'll want to demonstrate how your work fits into the big picture that they have.
ستحاول تحقيق الصورة الكبيرة والوصول للهدف الذي يريده العميل.
Sometimes, we all get too bogged down with the details and we seem to forget
أحيانًا ننشغل بالتفاصيل وننسى
the big picture in mind and that may happen with the client as well.
الصورة الكبيرة في ذهن العميل، وقد يحدث هذا مع العميل أيضًا.
But if you as a freelancer keep pointing back to
ولكن كموظف حر إذا كنت تستمر في الإشارة إلى
the big picture and how our small steps are leading towards it,
الصورة الذهنية الكبيرة وكيف تمهد الخطوات الصغيرة الطريق إليها،
it would be very valuable for the client.
سُيقدر العميل هذا الأمر.
Do not only put things in perspective,
لا تضع الأمور في منظورها فحسب،
but to also remind them of why we are working on
ولكن ذكر العميل بسبب عملك على
the current problem at hand and how it fits into the big picture.
المشكلة الحالية وكيف يساهم حلها في الوصول للصورة الكبيرة.
This one in fact further reaffirm to the client that you are
وهذه النقطة ستؤكد للعميل أنك
thinking in their lines and they can trust you for the work on the project.
تفكر في مصلحته وسيستطيع أن يثق بك في العمل على المشروع.
Now an example of this kind of communication could be this,
وكمثال على هذا الأسلوب من التواصل
when you're talking about why a GPS location detector is being built in the app and
عندما تتحدث عن سبب بناء إمكانية تعقب موقع لتحديد المواقع في التطبيق
how it fits into their model for their primary user segment or something like this,
وكيف يتناسب ذلك مع نموذجه لشريحة المستخدم الرئيسي أو شيء من هذا القبيل،
reaffirming the client what advantage will be
والتأكيد للعميل بالميزة
gained with the front-end framework that is being used,
المكتسبة من خلال إطار الواجهة الأمامية الذي يتم استخدامه،
emphasizing on its mobile responsiveness and what use case or would be most useful then.
مع التأكيد على استجابته السريعة والحالة المُستخدم فيها أو أنها ستحقق فائدة أكبر.